<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>Relevant Patient Benefit of Sublingual <lb/>Immunotherapy with Birch Pollen Allergen Extract <lb/>in Allergic Rhinitis: An Open, Prospective, Non-<lb/>Interventional Study <lb/>Christine Blome . Meike Hadler . Efstrathios Karagiannis . <lb/>Julia Kisch . Christopher Neht . Nora Kressel . Matthias Augustin <lb/>Received: February 19, 2020 / Published online: April 28, 2020 <lb/>Ó The Author(s) 2020 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Introduction: Sublingual <lb/>immunotherapy <lb/>(SLIT) with birch pollen extract has been shown <lb/>to be an efficacious treatment of allergic rhinitis <lb/>(AR). An as-yet unanswered question is whether <lb/>and how clinical benefit translates into patient <lb/>benefit, i.e. what benefit patients derive from <lb/>this treatment. <lb/>Methods: This 1-year, open, prospective, mul-<lb/>ticenter, non-interventional study conducted in <lb/>75 German centers measured patient-relevant <lb/>benefit of birch pollen SLIT (Staloral Ò Birch) <lb/>using the questionnaire &apos;&apos;Patient Benefit Index <lb/>for Allergic Rhinitis (PBI-AR)&apos;&apos;. At treatment <lb/>onset, patients rated the importance of 25 <lb/>treatment needs; after the first birch pollen <lb/>season on treatment, goal achievement was <lb/>evaluated. A preference-weighted benefit index <lb/>was calculated and its association with gender, <lb/>asthma, allergy status, and severity of AR <lb/>symptoms was determined. <lb/>Results: Mean age of the 291 adult patients was <lb/>38.8 years; 58.4% were female. The most <lb/>important treatment goals were to &apos;&apos;be able to <lb/>stay outdoors without symptoms&apos;&apos; (87.3% quite <lb/>or very important), &apos;&apos;no longer have a runny or <lb/>stuffed-up nose&apos;&apos; (86.9%), and &apos;&apos;be able to <lb/>breathe through your nose more freely&apos;&apos; <lb/>(86.9%). The treatment goals with the highest <lb/>benefit ratings (referring to those patients to <lb/>whom the respective goal applied) were to <lb/>&apos;&apos;have confidence in the therapy&apos;&apos; (60.5% has <lb/>helped &apos;&apos;quite&apos;&apos; or &apos;&apos;very much&apos;&apos;), &apos;&apos;have an easily <lb/>applicable treatment&apos;&apos; (55.6%), and &apos;&apos;be able to <lb/>breathe through my nose more freely&apos;&apos; (51.7%). <lb/>The average PBI-AR global score was 2.19 (SD <lb/>1.04) (0-4; with 4 indicating maximum benefit). <lb/>No significant differences in PBI-AR global score <lb/>or subscales were found between men and <lb/>women, poly-and monoallergic patients, or <lb/>patients with severe versus mild rhinoconjunc-<lb/>tivitis. Patients with asthma reported relevant <lb/>but lower benefit than patients without asthma. <lb/>Conclusion: After 1 year of birch pollen SLIT <lb/>treatment, patients reported considerable ben-<lb/>efit, mainly due to a reduction of physical <lb/>symptoms and treatment burden. <lb/>Digital Features To view digital features for this article <lb/>go to https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.12091017. <lb/>C. Blome (&amp;) Á J. Kisch Á C. Neht Á N. Kressel Á <lb/>M. Augustin <lb/>Institute for Health Services Research in <lb/>Dermatology and Nursing (IVDP), University <lb/>Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf (UKE), <lb/>Martinistr. 52, 20246 Hamburg, Germany <lb/>e-mail: c.blome@uke.de <lb/>M. Hadler <lb/>Stallergenes GmbH, Carl-Friedrich-Gauß-Straße 50, <lb/>47475 Kamp-Lintfort, Germany <lb/>E. Karagiannis <lb/>Stallergenes Greer, 6 Rue Alexis de Tocqueville, <lb/>92160 Antony, France <lb/>Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12325-020-01345-7 <lb/>Keywords: Birch <lb/>pollen; <lb/>Patient-relevant <lb/>benefit; <lb/>Patient-reported <lb/>outcomes; <lb/>Rhinoconjunctivitis; <lb/>Sublingual <lb/>immunotherapy; Treatment goals <lb/>Key Summary Points <lb/>Why carry out this study? <lb/>Allergic rhinitis has significant impact on <lb/>patient well-being. <lb/>Sublingual immunotherapy with birch <lb/>pollen extract has proven clinical benefit <lb/>in allergic rhinitis. <lb/>This study evaluates whether and how this <lb/>clinical benefit translates into patient-<lb/>reported and patient-relevant benefit <lb/>1 year after treatment onset. <lb/>What was learned from the study? <lb/>Most patients perceived the treatment as <lb/>at least partially successful in achieving <lb/>their self-defined treatment goals, in <lb/>particular with regard to physical <lb/>symptoms and treatment burden. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Allergic rhinitis (AR), with or without conjunc-<lb/>tivitis, is one of the most common <lb/>Immunoglobulin E (IgE)-mediated atopic dis-<lb/>eases [1]. It is an allergic reaction caused by IgE-<lb/>mediated inflammation of the nasal mucosa <lb/>which is triggered by a previous sensitization <lb/>against an allergen. Characteristic symptoms of <lb/>AR include sneezing, nasal congestion, rhinor-<lb/>rhoea, and nasal pruritus. <lb/>AR is a high-prevalence disease in many <lb/>developed countries [2-4]. In the European <lb/>general population, the prevalence of allergic <lb/>rhinitis was found to be around 25% [2]. <lb/>AR is a disease with &apos;&apos;uncontrolled symp-<lb/>toms, impaired quality of life, and unpleasant <lb/>comorbidities&apos;&apos; [5], having a significant impact <lb/>on patients&apos; well-being [6]. Besides AR <lb/>symptoms, affected patients can suffer from <lb/>impaired concentration, sleeping disorders, <lb/>irritability, decreased performance at school or <lb/>work, avoidance of outdoor activities, and <lb/>higher risk for infections. Moreover, AR is <lb/>associated with numerous comorbidities, and it <lb/>is a strong risk factor for the development of <lb/>allergic asthma: 15-38% of patients with AR <lb/>have asthma comorbidity [7]. <lb/>The management of AR is aimed at control-<lb/>ling symptoms and reducing inflammation. It <lb/>includes three key pillars: allergen avoidance, <lb/>targeted pharmacological treatment, and aller-<lb/>gen immunotherapy (AIT). Of these, AIT is the <lb/>only mechanistic-based treatment able to alter <lb/>the natural course of the disease, with long-<lb/>term effects after discontinuation of treatment <lb/>[8]. In addition to improving AR severity, AIT <lb/>can also successfully prevent the development <lb/>of associated diseases, such as allergic bronchial <lb/>asthma [9]. <lb/>The clinical efficacy of AIT in the treatment <lb/>of AR and/or asthma has been shown for several <lb/>standardized AIT products in randomized con-<lb/>trolled clinical trials [8, 10]. However, in addi-<lb/>tion to clinical efficacy, it is pivotal to <lb/>determine the benefit of a treatment in real-life <lb/>clinical practice from the patients&apos; perspective, <lb/>i.e. to determine whether clinical benefit <lb/>translates into patient benefit. Perceived benefit <lb/>is crucial, not only as a pivotal endpoint in itself <lb/>but also because it can be expected to increase <lb/>treatment satisfaction and adherence to treat-<lb/>ment, and can subsequently help to improve <lb/>treatment efficacy. Benefit will depend on the <lb/>patients&apos; treatment goals and expectations, <lb/>which in turn are determined by their individ-<lb/>ual life style, circumstances, and preferences. <lb/>Patients&apos; expectations often go beyond mea-<lb/>surable symptom reductions [11]. Besides a <lb/>relief of symptoms, patients generally expect a <lb/>reduction of morbidity, improvement in quality <lb/>of life, and a reduction of treatment burden <lb/>(defined as the workload of healthcare for the <lb/>patients and its impact on patient functioning <lb/>and well-being [12]). The benefit that a treat-<lb/>ment has in patients&apos; lives can only be evalu-<lb/>ated by the patients themselves, not by the <lb/>treating clinicians. <lb/></body>

			<front>Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></front>

			<page>2933 <lb/></page>

			<body>Focussing on birch pollen allergy, a major <lb/>source of AR in Europe [13], the aim of this real-<lb/>life medical practice study was to determine the <lb/>patient-relevant benefit of a birch pollen sub-<lb/>lingual immunotherapy (SLIT) treatment from <lb/>the AR patients&apos; perspective by using the Patient <lb/>Benefit Index Allergic Rhinitis (PBI-AR). The <lb/>efficacy of this birch pollen SLIT treatment had <lb/>been shown previously in two double-blind, <lb/>placebo-controlled randomized clinical trials <lb/>[14, 15]. <lb/>The PBI-AR is a standardized and validated <lb/>instrument which has been shown to be corre-<lb/>lated with treatment satisfaction, patient <lb/>health-related quality of life, and treatment <lb/>burden, with more satisfied and less burdened <lb/>patients showing higher patient benefit [11]. <lb/>The PBI-AR global benefit score was the pri-<lb/>mary outcome of this study. In further analyses, <lb/>we aimed to determine the distribution of <lb/>treatment goals, goal achievement, and PBI-AR <lb/>subscale scores, and to determine associations <lb/>of the PBI-AR with a number of patient char-<lb/>acteristics as well as global benefit ratings by <lb/>patients and physicians. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Study Design <lb/>This was a 1-year, open, prospective, multicen-<lb/>ter, non-interventional study in patients treated <lb/>with birch pollen SLIT. The study protocol was <lb/>approved by the Freiburg Ethics Commission <lb/>International. Patients gave written informed <lb/>consent and the study conformed with the <lb/>Helsinki Declaration of 1964, as revised in 2013, <lb/>concerning human rights. <lb/>Procedures <lb/>Patients were recruited between autumn 2012 <lb/>and the first quarter of 2013 by 75 allergologi-<lb/>cally experienced specialists (mainly ear, nose, <lb/>and throat physicians, dermatologists, and <lb/>pulmonologists) working in secondary care <lb/>across Germany. Each investigator was asked to <lb/>recruit three or more consecutive patients for <lb/>whom the decision to initiate birch pollen SLIT <lb/>had already been taken. The nationwide <lb/>recruitment of investigators and consecutive <lb/>enrolment of eligible patients should ensure <lb/>that a representative sample from the patient <lb/>population was selected. Patients were included <lb/>in the study after the decision for birch pollen <lb/>SLIT had already been made. <lb/>Eligible for this study were male or female <lb/>patients (C 18 years) presenting with birch pol-<lb/>len-induced allergic rhinitis, conjunctivitis, <lb/>rhinoconjunctivitis, and/or mild asthma con-<lb/>firmed by a positive skin prick test and/or a <lb/>positive serum titre of specific IgE, and who <lb/>gave their written informed consent. Exclusion <lb/>criteria were: hypersensitivity to any of the <lb/>excipients of the sublingual solution; immune <lb/>deficiency or autoimmune diseases; malignant <lb/>diseases; uncontrolled or severe asthma [forced <lb/>expiratory volume in 1 s (FEV 1 ) \ 70% of pre-<lb/>dicted value]; or inflammatory conditions in <lb/>the oral cavity. <lb/>Two visits were planned during the observa-<lb/>tion phase: a study initiation visit at the <lb/>beginning of treatment and a study end visit <lb/>after the first birch pollen season with SLIT <lb/>(birch pollen season 2013). During each visit, <lb/>investigators completed an electronic case <lb/>report form (eCRF) for each patient, while <lb/>patients filled in a paper-based questionnaire. <lb/>At the first visit, investigators documented <lb/>baseline data, such as demographic data, medi-<lb/>cal history (clinical manifestations of the <lb/>allergy. i.e. rhinitis, conjunctivitis, asthma, <lb/>atopic dermatitis; concomitant allergies), con-<lb/>comitant diseases and medication, impairment <lb/>due to allergic symptoms in the tree pollen <lb/>season before birch pollen SLIT treatment start <lb/>[Allergic Rhinitis Impact on Asthma (ARIA) <lb/>classification of allergic rhinitis symptoms, <lb/>severity of symptoms], and start date of SLIT. <lb/>Patients assessed their patient needs, i.e. their <lb/>treatment-related expectations. At the second <lb/>visit, documentation included data on treat-<lb/>ment, impairment due to allergic symptoms <lb/>during the first tree pollen season on SLIT <lb/>treatment, and treatment-related patient bene-<lb/>fit. Physicians&apos; and patients&apos; judgements on <lb/>improvement in well-being were also assessed at <lb/>the second visit. <lb/></body>

			<page>2934 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<body>In this article, we report the main outcomes <lb/>of the study, i.e. patient needs/expectations and <lb/>benefits as measured with the Patient Benefit <lb/>Index (PBI). <lb/>Study Treatment <lb/>Patients were treated with Staloral Ò Birch 300 <lb/>IR/ml (Stallergenes, Antony, France), a sublin-<lb/>gual solution of standardized birch pollen <lb/>allergen extract at a concentration of 10 IR/ml <lb/>(during the titration phase) and 300 IR/ml <lb/>(during both the titration and maintenance <lb/>phases). IR (= index of reactivity) is an in-house <lb/>unit to express biological activity. Treatment <lb/>was initiated with an 11-day titration phase <lb/>with increasing doses of the 10 IR/ml (1, 2, 4, 6, <lb/>8, and 10 puffs) and the 300 IR/ml concentra-<lb/>tion (1, 2, 4, 6, and 8 puffs), followed by a <lb/>maintenance phase. According to the investi-<lb/>gators&apos; prescriptions, patients took 4 or 8 puffs <lb/>of the 300 IR/ml concentration once daily dur-<lb/>ing the maintenance phase, following either a <lb/>perennial or a pre-/co-seasonal treatment <lb/>schedule. The extract had to be placed directly <lb/>under the tongue and kept there for 2 min <lb/>before being swallowed. <lb/>The Patient Benefit Index <lb/>The PBI is a standardized and validated instru-<lb/>ment that measures patient-reported treatment <lb/>needs and benefits; there are both a standard <lb/>version for dermatological indications [16] and <lb/>an indication-specific version. Each PBI version <lb/>consists of 2 questionnaires: The Patient Needs <lb/>Questionnaire (PNQ) is filled in before treat-<lb/>ment. It consists of standardized items on pre-<lb/>defined treatment goals that refer to symptom <lb/>reduction (e.g. &apos;&apos;no longer have a runny or <lb/>stuffed up nose&apos;&apos;; &apos;&apos;not have sneezing impulses <lb/>anymore&apos;&apos;), but also to improvement of quality <lb/>of life (e.g. &apos;&apos;be able to engage in normal leisure <lb/>activities&apos;&apos;) and low burden of the treatment <lb/>itself (e.g. &apos;&apos;have fewer side effects&apos;&apos;). Patients <lb/>rate the importance of each goal on a Likert <lb/>scale ranging from 0 = &apos;&apos;not at all [important]&apos;&apos; <lb/>to 4 = &apos;&apos;very [important]&apos;&apos;. The Patient Benefit <lb/>Questionnaire (PBQ) is filled in during or after <lb/>therapy. It consists of the same items as the <lb/>PNQ, but the instructions differ. Here, the <lb/>patients rate the extent to which the treatment <lb/>needs have been achieved by therapy using a <lb/>Likert scale ranging from 0 = &apos;&apos;not at all&apos;&apos; to <lb/>4 = &apos;&apos;very&apos;&apos;. As an alternative, the patient can <lb/>tick &apos;&apos;does not apply to me&apos;&apos; in the PNQ and &apos;&apos;did <lb/>not apply to me&apos;&apos; in the PBQ; in that case, the <lb/>item is considered irrelevant for further proce-<lb/>dures. A weighted index value, the actual PBI, is <lb/>calculated by multiplying the achieved benefits <lb/>(PBQ) with the importance of the respective <lb/>needs prior to therapy (PNQ), dividing these <lb/>products by the sum of all importance items <lb/>and summing them up for all items. The PBI <lb/>ranges from 0 (no benefit) to 4 (maximal bene-<lb/>fit). A PBI score [ 1 is considered relevant; this <lb/>cut-off was based on correlations with conver-<lb/>gent criteria (unpublished data). <lb/>In this study, the PBI version for patients <lb/>with allergic rhinitis (PBI-AR) was used. It <lb/>includes items on needs and benefits that are <lb/>specifically relevant for this patient group. The <lb/>PBI-AR has been validated in adult patients with <lb/>allergic rhinitis [11]. For the PBI-AR, both a <lb/>global score on overall benefit and subscales <lb/>scores on different dimensions of benefit (psy-<lb/>chological burden, treatment burden, physical <lb/>symptoms, activity/physical capability) can be <lb/>computed. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>In addition to descriptive analyses (frequency, <lb/>mean, standard deviation, median, interquartile <lb/>range, range), associations of PBI-AR global <lb/>score and subscale scores with patient charac-<lb/>teristics were determined. <lb/>We used the t-test for independent samples <lb/>for binary characteristics: gender; poly-versus <lb/>monoallergic patients; patients with versus <lb/>without asthma; mild versus severe rhinocon-<lb/>junctivitis; intermittent versus persistent aller-<lb/>gic rhinitis, according to the ARIA classification <lb/>[17]; decrease in rhinitis symptom, yes versus <lb/>no; decrease in conjunctivitis symptoms, yes <lb/>versus no. For the latter two variables, patients <lb/>were classified into the two groups based on the <lb/>physicians&apos; judgement on symptoms at first and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<page>2935 <lb/></page>

			<body>second visit with the response options &apos;&apos;none&apos;&apos;, <lb/>&apos;&apos;mild&apos;&apos;, &apos;&apos;moderate&apos;&apos;, and &apos;&apos;severe&apos;&apos;; patients <lb/>without symptoms at first visit were excluded <lb/>from this analysis. <lb/>Analyses of variance were used for compar-<lb/>isons between three groups (improvement in <lb/>well-being as rated by physicians and patients, <lb/>respectively: &apos;&apos;much better&apos;&apos;, &apos;&apos;somewhat better&apos;&apos;, <lb/>or &apos;&apos;unchanged&apos;&apos;). For these analyses, the sub-<lb/>groups with the response &apos;&apos;worse&apos;&apos; had to be <lb/>excluded for being too small for inclusion in the <lb/>statistical analysis (physicians: n = 4; patients: <lb/>n = 8). <lb/>This was a per-protocol analysis; no missing <lb/>data were imputed. Data were analyzed using <lb/>SPSS v.22 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>General Epidemiological Data <lb/>Data were available for 346 participants. Of <lb/>these, 20 were excluded from the overall anal-<lb/>ysis due to age \ 18 years (n = 7), retrospective <lb/>documentation (n = 10), or failure to take the <lb/>birch pollen SLIT (n = 3). Another 35 patients <lb/>were excluded from the PBI analysis because <lb/>they completed the PBI at the wrong time <lb/>point, namely: (1) the PNQ was completed later <lb/>than 21 days after treatment onset (at this time, <lb/>treatment effects may already be present, which <lb/>may influence the needs rating), (2) the PNQ <lb/>was completed after the start of the birch pollen <lb/>season, (3) the PBQ was completed before the <lb/>birch pollen season, or (4) the PBQ was com-<lb/>pleted before treatment onset. <lb/>Of 291 patients included in the PBI analysis, <lb/>42 had completed neither the PNQ nor the PBQ. <lb/>Thus, 249 patients with partial or complete PBI <lb/>data remained. Of these, 4 had not completed <lb/>the PNQ, and 33 had not completed the PBQ; <lb/>for the remaining 212 patients, PBI global scores <lb/>could be calculated. <lb/>Mean age of the 291 patients was 38.8 [s-<lb/>tandard deviation (SD) = 13.0] years with a <lb/>range of 18-78 years (Table 1), 58.4% were <lb/>female, and 74.2% were diagnosed with allergic <lb/>conjunctivitis in addition to allergic rhinitis <lb/>(the latter present in 98.6%; Table 1). Birch <lb/>pollen allergy was most prevalent (99.7%; <lb/>Table 1). <lb/>Table 1 Patient characteristics at first visit (n = 291) <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>n (% of 291) <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>121 (41.6) <lb/>Female <lb/>170 (58.4) <lb/>Symptoms <lb/>Allergic rhinitis <lb/>287 (98.6) <lb/>Intermittent a <lb/>94 (32.5) <lb/>Persistent a <lb/>195 (67.5) <lb/>Allergic conjunctivitis <lb/>216 (74.2) <lb/>Severity of rhinoconjunctivitis symptoms b <lb/>Mild <lb/>59 (20.3) <lb/>Severe <lb/>232 (79.7) <lb/>Asthma <lb/>66 (22.7) <lb/>Tree pollen allergy to <lb/>Birch <lb/>290 (99.7) <lb/>Alder <lb/>222 (76.3) <lb/>Hazel <lb/>212 (72.9) <lb/>Concomitant allergies (other than tree pollen) <lb/>No (= monoallergic patient) <lb/>127 (43.6) <lb/>Yes (= polyallergic patient) <lb/>164 (56.4) <lb/>Age <lb/>Mean (SD) [years] <lb/>38.8 (13.0) <lb/>Range [years] <lb/>18-78 <lb/>a According to ARIA classification [17]: Intermittent AR <lb/>symptoms occurring \ 4 days a week OR \ 4 consecutive <lb/>weeks; Persistent AR symptoms occurring [ 4 days a week <lb/>AND [ 4 consecutive weeks <lb/>b Severe rhinoconjunctivitis was assumed if the sum of the <lb/>severity assessments for rhinitis and conjunctivitis symp-<lb/>toms was C 4, with the following response options for <lb/>each of the two variables (physician global ratings): <lb/>0 = none, 1 = mild, 2 = moderate, 3 = severe <lb/></body>

			<page>2936 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2 Patient-rated importance of goals in birch pollen sublingual immunotherapy (SLIT) treatment, as measured with <lb/>the Patient Needs Questionnaire (PNQ) within the PBI-AR (first visit; n = 245 patients who completed the PNQ at least <lb/>partially) <lb/>Item (treatment goal) <lb/>As a result of therapy, how <lb/>important is it for you to… <lb/>n <lb/>Importance <lb/>rating <lb/>mean (SD) a <lb/>Does apply: <lb/>n (% of n = 245) <lb/>Importance rating: n (% of n = 245) <lb/>Not at all/somewhat/ <lb/>moderately/ <lb/>does not apply <lb/>Quite/ <lb/>very <lb/>1. … Not have sneezing impulses <lb/>anymore (S3) <lb/>245 3.26 (0.99) 243 (99.2) <lb/>51 (20.8) <lb/>194 (79.2) <lb/>2. … No longer have a runny or <lb/>stuffed up nose (S3) <lb/>245 3.51 (0.83) 244 (99.6) <lb/>32 (13.1) <lb/>213 (86.9) <lb/>3. … Be able to breathe through your <lb/>nose more freely (S3) <lb/>244 3.45 (0.92) 241 (98.4) <lb/>32 (13.1) <lb/>213 (86.9) <lb/>4. … Feel less fatigued or groggy (S4) 245 2.93 (1.25) 227 (92.7) <lb/>74 (30.2) <lb/>171 (69.8) <lb/>5…. Be able to stay outdoors without <lb/>symptoms (S3) <lb/>244 3.44 (0.88) 241 (98.4) <lb/>31 (12.7) <lb/>214 (87.3) <lb/>6…. Feel less irritated (S1) <lb/>245 2.32 (1.49) 213 (86.9) <lb/>121 (49.4) <lb/>124 (50.6) <lb/>7…. Have an easily applicable <lb/>treatment (S2) <lb/>244 2.87 (1.30) 224 (91.4) <lb/>81 (33.2) <lb/>164 (66.8) <lb/>8…. Not have itching on the eyes, <lb/>nose or palate anymore (S3) <lb/>245 3.17 (1.26) 232 (94.7) <lb/>53 (21.6) <lb/>192 (78.4) <lb/>9…. Not have burning or watery eyes <lb/>anymore (S3) <lb/>245 3.17 (1.24) 232 (94.7) <lb/>54 (22.0) <lb/>191 (78.0) <lb/>10…. Be healed of all symptoms (S3) 245 3.16 (1.25) 227 (92.7) <lb/>50 (20.4) <lb/>195 (79.6) <lb/>11…. Be able to sleep better (S1) <lb/>245 2.75 (1.45) 213 (86.9) <lb/>83 (34.0) <lb/>162 (66.0) <lb/>12…. Feel less depressed (S1) <lb/>245 2.31 (1.50) 206 (84.1) <lb/>122 (49.8) <lb/>123 (50.2) <lb/>13…. Experience a greater enjoyment <lb/>of life (S1) <lb/>245 2.32 (1.54) 201 (82.0) <lb/>120 (49.0) <lb/>125 (51.0) <lb/>14…. Have no fear that the disease <lb/>will become worse (S1) <lb/>245 2.54 (1.49) 212 (86.5) <lb/>103 (42.0) <lb/>142 (58.0) <lb/>15…. Be more productive in everyday <lb/>life (S4) <lb/>245 2.99 (1.21) 232 (94.7) <lb/>68 (27.8) <lb/>177 (72.2) <lb/>16…. Be able to engage in normal <lb/>leisure activities (S4) <lb/>244 3.20 (1.05) 238 (97.1) <lb/>48 (19.7) <lb/>197 (80.3) <lb/>17…. Be comfortable showing <lb/>yourself more in public (S1) <lb/>242 1.93 (1.54) 192 (78.5) <lb/>147 (59.9) <lb/>98 (40.1) <lb/>18…. Be able to concentrate better at <lb/>work (S4) <lb/>245 2.62 (1.48) 211 (86.1) <lb/>93 (38.0) <lb/>152 (62.0) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<page>2937 <lb/></page>

			<body>Patient-Relevant Needs <lb/>Patient needs/expectations are shown in <lb/>Table 2. The most important treatment goals <lb/>were to &apos;&apos;be able to stay outdoors without <lb/>symptoms&apos;&apos; (&apos;&apos;quite&apos;&apos; or &apos;&apos;very&apos;&apos; important to <lb/>87.3% of patients), &apos;&apos;no longer have a runny or <lb/>stuffed up nose&apos;&apos; (86.9%), &apos;&apos;be able to breathe <lb/>through your nose more freely&apos;&apos; (86.9%), and <lb/>&apos;&apos;be able to engage in normal leisure activities&apos;&apos; <lb/>(80.3%). The lowest importance was found for <lb/>the goal to &apos;&apos;be able to have a normal sex life&apos;&apos; <lb/>(34.4%). Generally, expectations related to the <lb/>reduction of physical symptoms received the <lb/>highest mean ratings from the patients, i.e. were <lb/>considered most important. <lb/>Patient-Relevant Benefit <lb/>Patient assessments of benefits provided by <lb/>birch pollen SLIT are detailed in Table 3. The <lb/>treatment goals with the highest benefit ratings <lb/>(referring to those patients to whom the <lb/>respective goal applied) were to &apos;&apos;have confi-<lb/>dence in the therapy&apos;&apos; (has helped &apos;&apos;quite&apos;&apos; or <lb/>&apos;&apos;very much&apos;&apos; in 60.5% of patients), &apos;&apos;have an <lb/>easily applicable treatment&apos;&apos; (55.6%), &apos;&apos;be able to <lb/>breathe through my nose more freely&apos;&apos; (51.7%), <lb/>and &apos;&apos;not have sneezing impulses anymore&apos;&apos; <lb/>(51.2%). The lowest benefit ratings were given <lb/>for &apos;&apos;be less burdened in your partnership&apos;&apos; with <lb/>29.8% and &apos;&apos;be able to have a normal sex life&apos;&apos; <lb/>with 30.7%. <lb/>Patient Benefit Index Global and Subscale <lb/>Scores <lb/>The average weighted PBI-AR global score on <lb/>overall treatment benefit of the birch pollen <lb/>SLIT was 2.19 (SD 1.04; Fig. 1; Table 4; possible <lb/>range 0-4 with 4 indicating maximum benefit). <lb/>A total of 81.1% patients (n = 172) attained an <lb/>at least minimally relevant benefit of 1.0 or <lb/>higher. For the subscale &apos;&apos;treatment burden&apos;&apos;, the <lb/>Table 2 continued <lb/>Item (treatment goal) <lb/>As a result of therapy, how <lb/>important is it for you to… <lb/>n <lb/>Importance <lb/>rating <lb/>mean (SD) a <lb/>Does apply: <lb/>n (% of n = 245) <lb/>Importance rating: n (% of n = 245) <lb/>Not at all/somewhat/ <lb/>moderately/ <lb/>does not apply <lb/>Quite/ <lb/>very <lb/>19…. Be less burdened in your <lb/>partnership (S1) <lb/>244 1.92 (1.57) 183 (74.6) <lb/>143 (58.2) <lb/>102 (41.8) <lb/>20…. Be able to have a normal sex <lb/>life (S1) <lb/>241 1.65 (1.62) 174 (71.0) <lb/>161 (65.6) <lb/>84 (34.4) <lb/>21…. Be less dependent on doctor <lb/>and clinic visits (S2) <lb/>244 2.47 (1.44) 213 (86.9) <lb/>112 (45.9) <lb/>133 (54.1) <lb/>22…. Need less time for daily <lb/>treatment (S2) <lb/>243 2.57 (1.40) 218 (88.9) <lb/>104 (42.4) <lb/>141 (57.6) <lb/>23…. Have fewer out-of-pocket <lb/>treatment expenses (S2) <lb/>245 2.51 (1.45) 226 (92.2) <lb/>113 (46.1) <lb/>132 (53.9) <lb/>24…. Have fewer side effects (S2) <lb/>245 2.65 (1.50) 216 (88.2) <lb/>100 (40.8) <lb/>145 (59.2) <lb/>25…. Have confidence in the therapy <lb/>(S2) <lb/>245 3.03 (1.32) 222 (90.6) <lb/>68 (27.8) <lb/>177 (72.2) <lb/>S1 item from subscale &apos; &apos;psychological burden&apos; &apos;, S2 item from subscale &apos; &apos;treatment burden&apos; &apos;, S3 item from subscale &apos; &apos;physical <lb/>symptoms&apos; &apos;, S4 item from subscale &apos; &apos;activity/physical capability&apos; &apos; <lb/>a Range 0 = no importance to 4 = highest importance <lb/></body>

			<page>2938 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 3 Patient-rated achievement of treatment goals due to the birch pollen sublingual immunotherapy (SLIT) treatment, <lb/>as measured with the Patient Benefit Questionnaire (PBQ) within the PBI-AR (second visit; n = 216 patients who <lb/>completed the PBQ at least partially) <lb/>Item (treatment benefit) <lb/>The current treatment <lb/>has helped me to… <lb/>n (number of <lb/>patients who <lb/>answered this <lb/>item and did <lb/>not choose &apos;&apos;did <lb/>not apply&apos;&apos;) <lb/>Benefit <lb/>rating: <lb/>mean <lb/>(SD) a <lb/>Does apply: n (% <lb/>of n = 216) <lb/>Benefit rating: n (% of <lb/>n = 216) <lb/>Not at <lb/>all/somewhat/ <lb/>moderately <lb/>Quite/ <lb/>very <lb/>1. … Not have sneezing impulses <lb/>anymore (S3) <lb/>215 <lb/>2.26 (1.18) 216 (100.0) <lb/>105 (48.8) <lb/>111 (51.2) <lb/>2. … No longer have a runny or <lb/>stuffed up nose (S3) <lb/>214 <lb/>2.22 (1.20) 214 (99.1) <lb/>110 (50.9) <lb/>106 (49.1) <lb/>3. … Be able to breathe through my <lb/>nose more freely (S3) <lb/>211 <lb/>2.32 (1.18) 213 (98.6) <lb/>104 (48.3) <lb/>112 (51.7) <lb/>4. … Feel less fatigued or groggy (S4) 205 <lb/>2.15 (1.23) 205 (94.9) <lb/>121 (56.1) <lb/>95 (43.9) <lb/>5. … Be able to stay outdoors without <lb/>symptoms (S3) <lb/>211 <lb/>2.12 (1.29) 212 (98.1) <lb/>122 (56.4) <lb/>94 (43.6) <lb/>6. … Feel less irritated (S1) <lb/>183 <lb/>1.85 (13.0) 185 (85.5) <lb/>138 (63.9) <lb/>78 (36.1) <lb/>7. … Have an easily applicable <lb/>treatment (S2) <lb/>207 <lb/>2.48 (1.27) 208 (96.3) <lb/>96 (44.4) <lb/>120 (55.6) <lb/>8. … Not have itching on the eyes, <lb/>nose or palate anymore (S3) <lb/>205 <lb/>2.24 (1.24) 205 (94.9) <lb/>112 (51.7) <lb/>104 (48.3) <lb/>9. … Not have burning or watery eyes <lb/>anymore (S3) <lb/>205 <lb/>2.25 (1.28) 206 (95.3) <lb/>106 (49.3) <lb/>110 (50.7) <lb/>10. … Be healed of all symptoms (S3) 204 <lb/>1.93 (1.35) 204 (94.4) <lb/>137 (63.2) <lb/>79 (36.8) <lb/>11. … Be able to sleep better (S1) <lb/>197 <lb/>2.15 (1.28) 198 (91.6) <lb/>123 (56.9) <lb/>93 (43.1) <lb/>12. … Feel less depressed (S1) <lb/>181 <lb/>1.93 (1.26) 181 (83.8) <lb/>132 (61.3) <lb/>84 (38.7) <lb/>13. … Experience a greater enjoyment <lb/>of life (S1) <lb/>184 <lb/>1.94 (1.25) 184 (85.2) <lb/>137 (63.6) <lb/>79 (36.4) <lb/>14. … Have no fear that the disease <lb/>will become worse (S1) <lb/>184 <lb/>2.08 (1.34) 184 (85.2) <lb/>115 (53.3) <lb/>101 (46.7) <lb/>15. … Be more productive in everyday <lb/>life (S4) <lb/>207 <lb/>2.13 (1.26) 207 (95.8) <lb/>119 (55.1) <lb/>97 (44.9) <lb/>16. … Be able to engage in normal <lb/>leisure activities (S4) <lb/>209 <lb/>2.15 (1.21) 209 (96.8) <lb/>120 (55.5) <lb/>96 (44.5) <lb/>17. … Be comfortable showing myself <lb/>more in public (S1) <lb/>171 <lb/>1.85 (1.25) 174 (80.7) <lb/>145 (67.3) <lb/>71 (32.7) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<page>2939 <lb/></page>

			<body>highest PBI-AR score was achieved with 2.26, <lb/>followed by &apos;&apos;physical symptoms&apos;&apos; with 2.15; for <lb/>&apos;&apos;psychological burden&apos;&apos;, the benefit was lowest <lb/>with 1.83 (Table 4). <lb/>Association of Treatment Benefit <lb/>with Other Outcomes <lb/>The PBI-AR global score was positively associ-<lb/>ated with an improvement in well-being as <lb/>rated by physicians and patients (Fig. 2). As <lb/>stated above, the subgroup with the response <lb/>&apos;&apos;worse&apos;&apos; had to be excluded due to small sample <lb/>sizes (physicians: n = 4; patients: n = 8). The <lb/>differences between the three groups (&apos;&apos;much <lb/>better&apos;&apos;, &apos;&apos;somewhat better&apos;&apos;, and &apos;&apos;unchanged&apos;&apos;) <lb/>were highly significant for both physicians&apos; and <lb/>patients&apos; judgement (p \ 0.001). <lb/>Furthermore, the PBI-AR global score was <lb/>positively associated with the decrease in <lb/>rhinitis symptoms as rated by the physicians. <lb/>Patients whose rhinitis symptoms had <lb/>improved in the birch pollen season with SLIT <lb/>treatment compared to the previous birch pol-<lb/>len season without treatment had a signifi-<lb/>cantly higher PBI-AR score (mean PBI-<lb/>AR = 2.31, SD = 1.03, n = 165) than patients <lb/>whose rhinitis symptoms had not decreased <lb/>(mean PBI-AR = 1.70, SD = 0.92, n = 44) <lb/>(p \ 0.001). <lb/>For conjunctivitis symptoms, however, the <lb/>PBI-AR in patients whose symptoms according <lb/>to the physicians&apos; judgement had decreased <lb/>Table 3 continued <lb/>Item (treatment benefit) <lb/>The current treatment <lb/>has helped me to… <lb/>n (number of <lb/>patients who <lb/>answered this <lb/>item and did <lb/>not choose &apos;&apos;did <lb/>not apply&apos;&apos;) <lb/>Benefit <lb/>rating: <lb/>mean <lb/>(SD) a <lb/>Does apply: n (% <lb/>of n = 216) <lb/>Benefit rating: n (% of <lb/>n = 216) <lb/>Not at <lb/>all/somewhat/ <lb/>moderately <lb/>Quite/ <lb/>very <lb/>18. … Be able to concentrate better <lb/>at work (S4) <lb/>194 <lb/>2.07 (1.22) 195 (90.2) <lb/>125 (57.7) <lb/>91 (42.3) <lb/>19. … Be less burdened in your <lb/>partnership (S1) <lb/>161 <lb/>1.75 (1.25) 163 (75.6) <lb/>152 (70.2) <lb/>64 (29.8) <lb/>20. … Be able to have a normal sex <lb/>life (S1) <lb/>153 <lb/>1.69 (1.32) 157 (72.9) <lb/>150 (69.3) <lb/>66 (30.7) <lb/>21. … Be less dependent on doctor <lb/>and clinic visits (S2) <lb/>186 <lb/>1.96 (1.30) 187 (86.5) <lb/>130 (60.2) <lb/>86 (39.8) <lb/>22. … Need less time for daily <lb/>treatment (S2) <lb/>198 <lb/>2.23 (1.29) 199 (92.1) <lb/>110 (51.0) <lb/>106 (49.0) <lb/>23. … Have fewer out-of-pocket <lb/>treatment expenses (S2) <lb/>203 <lb/>2.16 (1.35) 205 (94.9) <lb/>120 (55.7) <lb/>96 (44.3) <lb/>24. … Have fewer side effects (S2) 196 <lb/>2.31 (1.29) 199 (92.0) <lb/>109 (50.5) <lb/>107 (49.5) <lb/>25. … Have confidence in the <lb/>therapy (S2) <lb/>200 <lb/>2.55 (1.32) 201 (93.0) <lb/>85 (39.5) <lb/>131 (60.5) <lb/>S1 item from subscale &apos; &apos;psychological burden&apos; &apos;, S2 item from subscale &apos; &apos;treatment burden&apos; &apos;, S3 item from subscale &apos; &apos;physical <lb/>symptoms&apos; &apos;, S4 item from subscale &apos; &apos;activity/physical capability&apos; &apos; <lb/>a Range 0 = no benefit to 4 = highest benefit) <lb/></body>

			<page>2940 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<body>(mean PBI-AR = 2.24, SD 1.06, n = 144) was not <lb/>significantly higher than in patients whose <lb/>symptoms had not decreased (mean PBI-AR = <lb/>2.03, SD 0.84, n = 45) (p = 0.173). <lb/>Subgroup Analyses <lb/>The patient-relevant outcomes of birch pollen <lb/>SLIT as measured by the PBI-AR (Table 5) and its <lb/>subscales (data not shown) were not signifi-<lb/>cantly different regarding gender, concomitant <lb/>allergies (poly-vs. monoallergic patients), or <lb/>severity of rhinoconjunctivitis. Patients with <lb/>asthma showed lower treatment benefit than <lb/>patients without asthma in both PBI-AR global <lb/>scores and subscale scores. However, average <lb/>benefit in patients with asthma was well above <lb/>the cut-off value for minimal relevant benefit <lb/>(C 1). Patients with intermittent allergic rhinitis <lb/>had higher PBI-AR scores in the subscale on <lb/>&apos;&apos;physical symptoms&apos;&apos; than those with persistent <lb/>allergic rhinitis, but no significant differences <lb/>were found in the PBI-AR global score and in the <lb/>remaining subscales. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The aim of this study was to evaluate the <lb/>incremental therapeutic patient benefit from <lb/>SLIT with birch pollen extract in patients with <lb/>birch pollen-related allergic rhinoconjunctivi-<lb/>tis. In order to identify a broad spectrum of <lb/>patient-relevant needs and outcomes, the PBI <lb/>was used. Previous studies have demonstrated <lb/>its validity and feasibility in a variety of condi-<lb/>tions, including allergic rhinitis [11]. <lb/>At baseline, patients with birch pollen <lb/>induced AR had specific and multi-faceted <lb/>treatment needs, particularly related to relief <lb/>from physical symptoms of rhinitis, as well as <lb/>regarding the ability to have normal leisure <lb/>activities and to be outdoors. Treatment goals of <lb/>patients with AR reported in previous publica-<lb/>tions include symptom reduction, better sleep, <lb/>being able to undertake normal daily activities, <lb/>and not having side effects [17, 18], all of which <lb/>could be confirmed by the results of the present <lb/>study. <lb/>Fig. 1 Distribution of patient-relevant benefit from sub-<lb/>lingual immunotherapy (SLIT): PBI-AR global score, <lb/>ranged 0 = no benefit to 4 = maximum benefit <lb/>Table 4 Distribution of PBI-AR scores and subdimensions on patient-relevant benefit from birch pollen sublingual <lb/>immunotherapy (SLIT) treatment <lb/>n <lb/>Mean (SD) <lb/>Median (IQR) <lb/>Minimum-maximum <lb/>PBI-AR global score <lb/>212 <lb/>2.19 (1.04) <lb/>2.38 (1.37-3.01) <lb/>0.00-4.00 <lb/>PBI-AR subscale 1: &apos; &apos;psychological burden&apos; &apos; <lb/>192 <lb/>1.83 (1.12) <lb/>1.88 (1.00-2.64) <lb/>0.00-4.00 <lb/>PBI-AR subscale 2: &apos; &apos;treatment burden&apos; &apos; <lb/>202 <lb/>2.26 (0.40) <lb/>2.41 (1.48-3.17) <lb/>0.00-4.00 <lb/>PBI-AR subscale 3: &apos; &apos;physical symptoms&apos;&apos; <lb/>211 <lb/>2.15 (1.08) <lb/>2.43 (1.19-3.00) <lb/>0.00-4.00 <lb/>PBI-AR subscale 4: &apos; &apos;activity/physical capability&apos; &apos; <lb/>209 <lb/>2.06 (1.14) <lb/>2.17 (1.05-3.00) <lb/>0.00-4.00 <lb/>PBI-AR scores range from 0 = no benefit to 4 = maximum benefit <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<page>2941 <lb/></page>

			<body>After weighting the reported benefits item-<lb/>wise by the patients&apos; individual treatment <lb/>needs, a vast majority of patients (81%) showed <lb/>an at least clinically minimum relevant benefit <lb/>(PBI C 1), and the average PBI was 2.19. This <lb/>indicates that most patients who were treated <lb/>with birch pollen SLIT during the observation <lb/>phase of this study perceived the treatment as at <lb/>least partially successful in achieving their self-<lb/>defined treatment goals, in particular with <lb/>regard to the subscales &apos;&apos;physical symptoms&apos;&apos; <lb/>and &apos;&apos;treatment burden&apos;&apos;. Consequently, the <lb/>main advantages of birch pollen SLIT treatment <lb/>from the patients&apos; perspective were shown to be <lb/>an improvement of physical symptoms and a <lb/>low burden of treatment. <lb/>As the severity of AR and the combination of <lb/>AR and asthma are known to increase the <lb/>overall burden of the disease and the impact on <lb/>the patients [17, 18], and concomitant allergies <lb/>may reinforce the burden even further, patient <lb/>benefit was assessed in different subgroups of <lb/>patients. Regardless of the clinical profile, <lb/>patients benefited from treatment. Similar <lb/>mean PBI-AR global scores were obtained in <lb/>mono-and polyallergic patients and in patients <lb/>with mild versus severe symptoms. Patients <lb/>with asthma reported a patient-relevant benefit; <lb/>however, this benefit was lower than in patients <lb/>without asthma. In patients with persistent <lb/>allergic rhinitis, benefit was higher only with <lb/>regard to physical symptoms as compared to <lb/>patients with intermittent allergic rhinitis. The <lb/>reason for the lower response in these groups <lb/>could be a higher disease burden. As goal <lb/>achievement was rated by the patients them-<lb/>selves, patients from these subgroups may have <lb/>been more hesitant to give a very good benefit <lb/>assessment due to higher expectations on <lb/>treatment. <lb/>While the results allow for the conclusion <lb/>that patients regard the birch pollen SLIT <lb/>treatment as beneficial, this non-controlled <lb/>observational study has some limitations. <lb/>Effects due to other factors such as changes <lb/>in birch pollen load cannot be controlled for in <lb/>this kind of setting. However, according to data <lb/>from the German Pollen Information Service <lb/>[19], pollen load in Germany in 2013 was <lb/>markedly higher than in 2012, which supports <lb/>the hypothesis that the patient-reported symp-<lb/>tom improvement from 2012 to 2013 cannot be <lb/>attributed to a reduced pollen load. In addition, <lb/>this study aimed to assess treatment benefit of <lb/>Fig. 2 PBI-AR global score (mean and SD) by physicians&apos; and patients&apos; judgement on improvement in well-being (second <lb/>visit) <lb/></body>

			<page>2942 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<body>birch pollen SLIT from the patients&apos; perspective, <lb/>which implies that all needs and benefits data <lb/>represent the subjective view of the partici-<lb/>pants. Patients may understand items on need <lb/>and benefits in different ways, and the retro-<lb/>spective benefit judgement may be subject to <lb/>recall bias [20]. <lb/>PBI data from 35 participants (10.7% of 326) <lb/>were excluded from analysis because data were <lb/>collected at the wrong time, possibly because <lb/>patients&apos; appointments were re-scheduled and/ <lb/>or physicians and/or practice staff misremem-<lb/>bered the intended time points for assessment. <lb/>As this was a non-interventional study, observ-<lb/>ing treatment in routine medical practice, no <lb/>study site monitoring was conducted and devi-<lb/>ations from the planned assessments were to be <lb/>expected. <lb/>Additional analyses-i.e. all analyses except <lb/>for the evaluation of the PBI-AR global score-<lb/>should be interpreted with caution, as in these <lb/>explorative analyses significance values were <lb/>not adjusted for multiple testing. <lb/>AIT being a long-term treatment, the rec-<lb/>ommended treatment duration is at least <lb/>3 years [8]. While this study has demonstrated <lb/>patient-reported benefit of birch pollen SLIT <lb/>after one birch pollen season on treatment, <lb/>further investigation should be conducted to <lb/>evaluate sustained or long-term benefit over <lb/>more years of treatment, as indicated by exist-<lb/>ing clinical data: a clinical double-blind, pla-<lb/>cebo-controlled trial with the birch pollen SLIT <lb/>extracts used in this study showed a sustained <lb/>clinical efficacy after two seasons of treatment <lb/>[15]. Potentially, an increase in patient benefit <lb/>can be expected during the course of SLIT <lb/>treatment. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>Patients with AR reported considerable patient-<lb/>relevant treatment benefit from SLIT with a <lb/>birch pollen extract after one season of treat-<lb/>ment, mainly due to a reduction of physical <lb/>symptoms and treatment burden. This holds for <lb/>different patient groups, including both poly-<lb/>and monoallergic patients and patients with <lb/>mild and severe rhinoconjunctivitis. <lb/>Table 5 Comparison of PBI-AR global score indicating patient-relevant benefit from birch pollen sublingual <lb/>immunotherapy (SLIT) between patient subgroups (t-test for independent groups) <lb/>PBI-AR global score <lb/>n <lb/>Mean <lb/>(SD) <lb/>Difference between <lb/>means <lb/>95% CI of difference (lower <lb/>level to upper level) <lb/>p <lb/>Male patients <lb/>92 <lb/>2.25 (1.03) <lb/>0.12 <lb/>-0.17 to 0.40 <lb/>0.568 <lb/>Female patients <lb/>120 <lb/>2.14 (1.05) <lb/>Polyallergic patients <lb/>127 <lb/>2.18 (1.07) <lb/>-0.01 <lb/>-0.29 to 0.28 <lb/>0.954 <lb/>Monoallergic patients <lb/>85 <lb/>2.19 (1.01) <lb/>Mild rhinoconjunctivitis <lb/>39 <lb/>2.25 (1.05) <lb/>0.07 <lb/>-0.030 to 0.45 <lb/>0.694 <lb/>Severe rhinoconjunctivitis <lb/>173 <lb/>2.17 (1.04) <lb/>Non-asthmatic patients <lb/>160 <lb/>2.37 (0.91) <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.38 to 1.11 <lb/>\0.001 <lb/>Asthmatic patients <lb/>52 <lb/>1.62 (1.21) <lb/>Intermittent <lb/>rhinoconjunctivitis <lb/>65 <lb/>2.35 (0.96) <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-0.04 to 0.54 <lb/>0.094 <lb/>Persistent <lb/>rhinoconjunctivitis <lb/>146 <lb/>2.10 (1.07) <lb/>CI confidence interval <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<page>2943 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>The authors thank the participants of the study. <lb/>We also thank the Scientific Communication <lb/>Team of the IVDP, in particular Sara Tiedemann <lb/>and Mario Gehoff, for copy editing. <lb/>Funding. This study was supported by a <lb/>research grant from Stallergenes GmbH, <lb/>including the Rapid Service Fee and Open <lb/>Access Fee. <lb/>Authorship. All named authors meet the <lb/>International Committee of Medical Journal <lb/>Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship for this <lb/>article, take responsibility for the integrity of <lb/>the work as a whole, and have given their <lb/>approval for this version to be published.</div> <lb/>
			
			<div type="annex">Disclosures. Christine Blome, Christopher <lb/>Neht, Julia Kisch and Nora Kressel declare that <lb/>they have no conflict of interest. Meike Hadler <lb/>is an employee of Stallergenes GmbH. Efs-<lb/>trathios Karagiannis is the Director of Global <lb/>Medical Affairs at Stallergenes Greer. Matthias <lb/>Augustin has received a research grant for this <lb/>study from Stallergenes GmbH. <lb/>Compliance with Ethics Guidelines. The <lb/>study protocol was approved by the Freiburg <lb/>Ethics Commission International. Patients gave <lb/>written informed consent and the study con-<lb/>formed with the Helsinki Declaration of 1964, <lb/>as revised in 2013, concerning human rights.</div> <lb/>
			
			<div type="availability">Data Availability. The datasets analyzed <lb/>during the current study are available from the <lb/>corresponding author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>
			
			<front>Open Access</front>. 
			
			<div type="annex">This article is licensed under a <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommer-<lb/>cial 4.0 International License, which permits <lb/>any non-commercial use, sharing, adaptation, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium <lb/>or format, as long as you give appropriate credit <lb/>to the original author(s) and the source, provide <lb/>a link to the Creative Commons licence, and <lb/>indicate if changes were made. The images or <lb/>other third party material in this article are <lb/>included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons <lb/>licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit <lb/>line to the material. If material is not included <lb/>in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and <lb/>your intended use is not permitted by statutory <lb/>regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you <lb/>will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, <lb/>visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-<lb/>nc/4.0/. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Greiner AN, Hellings PW, Rotiroti G, Scadding GK. <lb/>Allergic rhinitis. Lancet. 2011;378(9809):2112-22. <lb/>2. Bauchau V, Durham SR. Prevalence and rate of <lb/>diagnosis of allergic rhinitis in Europe. Eur Respir J. <lb/>2004;24:758-64. <lb/>3. Dahl R, Andersen PS, Chivato T, et al. National <lb/>prevalence of respiratory allergic disorders. Respir <lb/>Med. 2004;98:398-403. <lb/>4. Warner JO, Kaliner MA, Crisci CD, et al. Allergy <lb/>practice worldwide: a report by the World Allergy <lb/>Organization Specialty and Training Council. Int <lb/>Arch Allergy Immunol. 2006;139:166-74. <lb/>5. Meltzer EO. Allergic rhinitis: burden of illness, <lb/>quality of life, comorbidities, and control. Immunol <lb/>Allergy Clin North Am. 2016;36(2):235-48. <lb/>6. Canonica GW, Bousquet J, Mullol J, Scadding GK, <lb/>Virchow JC. A survey of the burden of allergic <lb/>rhinitis in Europe. Allergy. 2007;62(Suppl 85): <lb/>17-25. <lb/>7. Bro _ <lb/>zek JL, Bousquet J, Agache I, et al. Allergic <lb/>rhinitis and its impact on asthma (ARIA) guidelines-<lb/>2016 revision. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2017;140(4): <lb/>950-8. <lb/>8. Roberts G, Pfaar O, Akdis CA, et al. EAACI guideli-<lb/>nes <lb/>on <lb/>allergen <lb/>immunotherapy: <lb/>allergic <lb/>rhinoconjunctivitis. Allergy. 2018;73:765-98. <lb/>9. Halken S, Larenas-Linnemann D, Roberts G, et al. <lb/>EAACI guidelines on allergen immunotherapy: <lb/>prevention of allergy. Pediatr Allergy Immunol. <lb/>2017;28:728-45. <lb/>10. Pfaar O, Bachert C, Bufe A, et al. Guideline on <lb/>allergen-specific immunotherapy in IgE-mediated <lb/>allergic diseases. Allergo J Int. 2014;23:28-65. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2944 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>11. Franzke N, Scha ¨fer I, Jost K, et al. A new instrument <lb/>for the assessment of patient-defined benefit in the <lb/>treatment of allergic rhinitis. Allergy. 2011;66(5): <lb/>665-70. <lb/>12. Eton DT, Ridgeway JL, Egginton JS, et al. Finalizing <lb/>a measurement framework for the burden of treat-<lb/>ment in complex patients with chronic conditions. <lb/>Patient Relat Outcome Meas. 2015;27(6):117-26. <lb/>13. Biedermann T, Winther L, Till SJ, Panzner P, Knulst <lb/>A, Valovirta E. Birch pollen allergy in Europe. <lb/>Allergy. 2019;74(7):1237-48. <lb/>14. Khinchi MS, Poulsen LK, Carat F, Andre C, Hansen <lb/>AB, Malling HJ. Clinical efficacy of sublingual and <lb/>subcutaneous <lb/>birch <lb/>pollen <lb/>allergen-specific <lb/>immunotherapy: a randomized, placebo-con-<lb/>trolled, double-blind, double-dummy study. <lb/>Allergy. 2004;59:45-53. <lb/>15. Worm M, Rak S, de Blay F, et al. Sustained efficacy <lb/>and safety of a 300 IR daily dose of a sublingual <lb/>solution of birch pollen allergen extract in adults <lb/>with allergic rhinoconjunctivitis: results of a dou-<lb/>ble-blind, placebo-controlled study. Clin Transl <lb/>Allergy. 2014;4:7. <lb/>16. Augustin M, Radtke MA, Zschocke I, et al. The <lb/>patient benefit index: a novel approach in patient-<lb/>defined outcomes measurement for skin diseases. <lb/>Arch Dermatol Res. 2009;301(8):561-71. <lb/>17. Bousquet J, Khaltaev N, Cruz AA, et al. Allergic <lb/>Rhinitis and its Impact on Asthma (ARIA) 2008 <lb/>update (in collaboration with the World Health <lb/>Organization, GA (2) LEN and AllerGen). Allergy. <lb/>2008;63(Suppl 86):8-160. <lb/>18. Price D, Scadding G, Ryan D, et al. The hidden <lb/>burden of adult allergic rhinitis: UK healthcare <lb/>resource utilisation survey. Clin Transl Allergy. <lb/>2015;5:39. <lb/>19. Stiftung Deutscher Polleninformationsdienst. Lit-<lb/>eratur und Vortra ¨ge-Studien, Analysen und <lb/>Vero ¨ffentlichungen. http://www.pollenstiftung.de/ <lb/>symposien-literatur/studienanalysen/. Accessed 13 <lb/>Feb 2020. <lb/>20. Blome C, Augustin M. Measuring change in quality <lb/>of life: bias in prospective and retrospective evalu-<lb/>ation. Value Health. 2015;18(1):110-5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Adv Ther (2020) 37:2932-2945 <lb/></note>

			<page>2945 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
